[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm reading some suttas in a chapter called Samācitta, the peaceful mind, in the Anguttara Nikaya.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a small one first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, eh... mendicants
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the virtuous only know how to be grateful and thankful.
[SPEAKER_00]: The good only know how to be grateful.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how... what is gratitude, you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: How is one truly grateful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by being virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the important bit to recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gratitude is not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I shall be grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I shall not be grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because often people think, oh, you should be great, makes yourself grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Sutta says, if you're virtuous, gratefulness is the result of it, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he can only know how to... only knows how to be grateful, a virtuous person.
[SPEAKER_01]: He only knows how to be virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of the virtue, he can only be grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: He cannot be ungrateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's gratefulness state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say all you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: I really appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm so grateful, but not really have that state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that state of mind of gratefulness is the result of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And consequently, state of mind of non-gratefulness is the result of lack of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: By being non-virtuous, you cannot appreciate
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you might get on that superficial level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, you are not in that frame of mind, because that frame of mind can only be developed through virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not a matter of choice to be grateful or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you never say you're grateful, and never say you appreciate anything, if you're virtuous, you are grateful, you appreciate everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue will make it as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are being... because you are being careful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you purchase.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are careful, you consider it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You consider things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... And that's already the... that type of outlook that is kind of... that leads to gratefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when people want sometimes make a practice of
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... yeah, it's not what you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not what you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the... it's the... what state of mind you have overall.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he might, like, and that's another thing, like, I think people would often genuinely conflate happiness, being pleased, with gratefulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you know, you made my wish come true.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm so grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'm really, like, I'm just happy because I got what I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't necessarily mean you're in a grateful state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you are grateful, then, the value of that which made you happy will not be lost, obscured, forgotten about.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm so grateful, I finally got what I want, which is a college fund, so I'll take it seriously.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will be effortless, because you're in a grateful state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yes, if you dismiss it, and then don't study, and don't act towards it, don't make the most of it, it means, oh, yeah, you were never grateful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were just happy, you got what you want, enjoyed the ideas of it, but then practically you were doing the opposite things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, it comes down to the action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Grateful comes from the virtuous behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you act virtuously, practice sense-restraint, and guard other sense-doors, you will be grateful, even for a little thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the value of it will not be obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: The value of it will not be second, put second, and you put yourself first, and your animal needs first, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will all be maintained in the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the gratefulness will remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Parents are very helpful to
[SPEAKER_01]: And the common thread to all of that is, basically, it's that bigger perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not just limited to this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it says, like, even if you were to establish them as supreme rulers, even if you give them everything in this world and make them the rulers of this world, with all the seven
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you establish them in generosity, that pertains now to future rebirths, in ethical conduct that pertains in future rebirths, in right view that pertains to future rebirths, oh, you would have paid them more than enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you would have paid not just for this life, but for... because they would have... they would have missed out on that, because unethical person will not benefit in the lives to come, because of their lacking of ethics.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same with virtue and others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you change that for them,
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, you repay them now for the illness to come, because you establish them in generosity, they will pertain, the results of that will pertain for a long time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you repay them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you say, okay, so you can set them up with a good lifestyle, with all the benefits of this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's very limited, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It stays just here, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And from their point of view, yeah, even if you give them everything in the world, technically you still can't repay them, because they gave you life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you give them more than this, not just this world, but all the next lives, yeah, in that way, you gave them future lives of a better kind, not being born in another realm and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you gave them future lives of a better kind, they gave you... Basically, fixing their lack of virtue, fixing their lack of faith, making them behave properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, see, that's how you repay them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even repaying your own parents, even the debt to your parents, none of that needs to be personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that needs to be on the level of attachment, like, yeah, but it's my parents, you know, I must emotionally get involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must forsake my my training in virtue and everything else, because I need to help my parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's your worldliness and lack of right view speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can stay impersonal, and you can focus on basically teaching them, getting through to them, because you know them, because they are your parents, and establish them in proper behavior, in faith, in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, don't dismiss it like, oh, I don't care.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you do actually owe them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They gave you life.
[SPEAKER_01]: They, as the sutta says, nurtured you and made everything else possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so you owe them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that does not mean this kind of, oh, I must, like, that whole relationship must always stay on the level of attachment and this emotional stickiness and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: random individuals passing through that, you know, collided with, and whatever else, and they'll carry on their own way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Beings are owners of their own actions, and that's the direction they'll be heading.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't matter how many sons and daughters you had, and how much they're helping you, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all bound with this world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so helping them, it's not on the level of
[SPEAKER_01]: My mother will be upset if I'm not here.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must be here, then, and forsake everything else that's important for the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not helping anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're there to establish her in virtue, and that's it, that's the extent, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if she's unhappy with you not being there, even if parents are unhappy with you leaving, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to help them on that level that actually matters, not just that makes them feel good.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when I first read that, you can't repay them, unless you set them up, esteeming your parent in generosity, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to start with yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't... Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yourself is not a virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will sort my parents, I give in, I teach them what generosity is, while I'm still...
[SPEAKER_01]: While you are not generous, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not virtuous, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you've got to... And that's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, you can teach them, by example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's already... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, you kind of accomplish two goals with one effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establish yourself in virtue and show the example that, you know, to those who will kind of learn from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the only path of getting there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, there is a kind of prerequisite for any successful teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, when people... you might be teaching people and they might make sense of what you're saying, but if they look and see you do the opposite, they will dismiss what you said, naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they look and see exactly what you're saying they should do, that you're already doing it and living it, then, okay, they can't argue with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, doing it yourself, establishing yourself and all that, it is kind of a prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_01]: To be highly unlikely and un-virtuous, you have even no concept of virtue or un-behavior, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would value establishing your own parents in virtue and behavior, when you yourself don't value it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's even more unlikely that you will not... that you will be successful while you yourself completely have no concept of virtue, ethical conduct, established parents in that, through just teaching them, and then they will take it on while you're doing completely the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, again, that's how to be... how to be truly grateful to your parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a hopeless perspective in regard to where the value and where the importance is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that can only come out of gratefulness, which can only come out of your own virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're virtuous and practice the sense of strength and guarding of the senses in the right way, like the way of the training, not on the way of the external duty, as you are
[SPEAKER_01]: Kusala literally means beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Akusala, unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that, you need perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually, people's perspective is very limited, and beneficial is that which is pleasing, and unbeneficial is that which is displeasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's kind of the criteria of how I feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it comes down the same to whether, you know, you're engaging with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always the same criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you have developed virtue, sense of strength, practice properly, develop that perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: of gratitude, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, then you would exactly see.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not beneficial to indulge in, oh, I'll just make my parents feel good, but I won't make any effort, because they always get upset when I start talking about a virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, now you just enable them in their feelings, and you kind of sacrifice your own perspective and reason, just so they feel good, and you feel good, and don't feel bothered.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not beneficial for anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if you maybe do that so that you can then talk about a virtue, not preach to them or something like... but try to get the message through genuinely, like to somebody you would want to help and save.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they're unaware they're dying of this illness and they could fix it, they don't know how, they don't even know that they are ill.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it's going to be some hassle and work and unpleasantness getting, you know, that message across.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you succeeded, yeah, you
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they suffer on account of your absence for the rest of their life, it's nothing, absolutely nothing, in comparison to what you did to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the meaning that you are for them, you know, that... Well, yeah, yeah, yeah, the perspective that they gained through that, so that you now stand for, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.